<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ds:DataStory xmlns:ds="http://example.com/ds/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xml:lang="en">
    <ds:Metadata>
        <dct:title>The 1918-19 flu epidemic in The Netherlands</dct:title>
        <dct:creator>Thomas de Groot</dct:creator>
        <dct:creator>Wouter Beek</dct:creator>
        <dct:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dct:license>
        <LandingPage>https://stories.datalegend.net/spanishFluNetherlands/</LandingPage>
    </ds:Metadata>
    <ds:Story>
        <ds:Block xml:id="b1" type="text" mime="text/markdown">
            <ds:Metadata>
                <dct:title>The dataset</dct:title>
            </ds:Metadata>
            <ds:Cues>
                <title-prologue># I. {$ds-Metadata/dct:title}</title-prologue>
            </ds:Cues>
            Thanks to the indexation efforts of archives and the
            [LINKS project](https://iisg.amsterdam/en/hsn/projects/links), large parts of the Dutch civil registry
            (_'Burgerlijke Stand'_) are now becoming available for historians. The death certificates used here are
            retrieved from [openarch.nl](https://www.openarch.nl/)
            (available [here](https://www.openarch.nl/exports/5cfb55ebaf9fe5aaf216f6da1229c632/)). From the individual 
            death certificates files per archive, one combined dataset was created. One challenge of working with these 
            certificates is that that the same certificate may have been indexed by more than one archive. These were 
            de-duplicated using a combination of date of death, location and similar full names (using string distances). 
            Key variables were subsequently cleaned and standardized, such as age at death, placenames, and occupations. 
            Using different string match combinations, place names were standardized against the 
            [Historical Dutch Toponyms dataset](https://iisg.amsterdam/en/hsn/data/place-names), to retrieve coordinates 
            and Amsterdam Codes. Occupations were matched against the file 
            [HSN Occupations](https://iisg.amsterdam/en/hsn/data/occupations) to retrieve HISCO, HISCLASS and HISCAM 
            categorizations. All related R scripts can be found at our [Github repository](https://github.com/CLARIAH/wp4-civreg).
            The dataset was then converted into Linked Data with [COW](https://github.com/CLARIAH/COW), using the "Persons table" 
            datamodel designed by Gerrit Bloothooft and Kees Mandemakers in the LINKS project. The complete Linked Dataset and the
            related metadata scheme can be explored at [Druid](https://druid.datalegend.net/dataLegend/deaths-1910-1920/)
            
            The table below demonstrates the success of the standardization efforts, presented as Linked Data. 
        </ds:Block>
        <ds:Block xml:id="b2" type="query" mime="sparql" href="queries/standardization_share.rq">
            <ds:Metadata>
                <dct:title>Share of death certificates with standardized places of death and occupations:</dct:title>
            </ds:Metadata>
        </ds:Block>
        <ds:Block xml:id="b3" type="text" mime="text/markdown">
            _Sources:_
            Gerrit Bloothooft &amp; Kees Mandemakers, 
            _[The Zeeland Challenge](http://www.gerritbloothooft.nl/Publications/The%20Zeeland%20Challenge%20v2-2.pdf)_, 
            document for benchmark, presented at workshop Data Linkage: Techniques, Challenges and Applications at Isaac 
            Newton Institute for Mathematics, Cambridge, UK, 15 September 2016; Van Leeuwen, M. H. D. , Maas, I. &amp; Miles, 
            A. (2003). _HISCO: Historical International Standard Classification of Occupations_. Leuven: Leuven University 
            Press; Zijdeman, R., &amp; Lambert, P. (2010). _Measuring social structure in the past: A comparison of historical
            class schemes and occupational stratification scales on Dutch 19th and early 20th century data_. Journal of Belgian
            History/Belgisch Tijdschrift voor Nieuwste Geschiedenis/Revue Belge de Histoire Contemporaine, 40(1-2), 111-141.
        </ds:Block>
        <ds:Block xml:id="b4" type="text" mime="text/markdown">
            Because archives generally decide for themselves which variables from the civil registry they will index, occupations
            of the deceased are not available for all regions. Archives from the provinces of Drenthe, Gelderland, and Zeeland are,
            regrettably, the only ones to have structurally indexed all occupations of the deceased for this period.
        </ds:Block>
        <ds:Block xml:id="b5" type="query" mime="sparql" href="queries/occupation_share.rq" >
            <ds:Metadata>
                <dct:title>Share of known occupations of the deceased, aged eighteen and over, by municipality:</dct:title>
            </ds:Metadata>
            <ds:Cues>
                <data-output>geo</data-output>
            </ds:Cues>
        </ds:Block>    
    </ds:Story>
    <ds:Data>
        <ds:Run ref="all" when="2022-03-16" mime="application/warc" href="flu.warc.gz"/>
        <ds:Run ref="b2" when="2022-03-30" mime="text/csv" href="data/standardization_share.csv"/>
        <ds:Run ref="b5" when="2022-03-30" mime="text/csv" href="img/occupation_share-geo.csv"/>
        <ds:Run ref="b5" when="2022-03-30" mime="image/png" href="img/occupation_share-geo.png"/>
    </ds:Data>
</ds:DataStory>
